Guide to the Brooklyn Navy Yard oral history collection ARC.003
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Oral History Interview with William Obitz, May 18, 2009; 2010.003.045
  Cooking; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); New Jersey; Pennsylvania; Jersey City (N.J.); Military life; Cooking for military personnel; Warships; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York Naval Shipyard; Missouri (Battleship: BB 63)
- Oral History Interview with Ida Pollack, March 20, 1989; 1995.005.005
  Ida Pollack (1922- ) grew up in the Bronx in a Jewish-American family. Her father was active in the International Workers Order (IWO), a Communist Party fraternal organization. Pollack was active in both the IWO shula (school) and the Young Communist League. She briefly attended Brooklyn College, but left to begin working, initially for a greeting card factory, then for Gimbels department store and eventually as a welder at the Brooklyn Navy Yard.
  Ida Pollack (1922- ) married in 1941 and began working at the Navy Yard shortly after her husband went into the service in 1942. During her interview, she discusses how she chose to be a welder in order to help the war effort, her training at the Navy Yard, working conditions and injuries, welding equipment, her fear of heights, and wages. Pollack remembers how her friend Sylvia [Honigsman Everitt] found out about her husbands death during their shift at the Navy Yard. Everitt was interviewed along with Pollack in 2008 (2010.003.019). During the interview, Pollack also recalls the death of another woman worker who fell into the dry dock. Pollack was laid off at the end of WWII and moved to Troy, New York for a few years where Pollack attempted to be a welder for again but had trouble because of her gender. Pollack later returned to New York City where she and her husband were very active in political organizations. Interview conducted by Diane Esses.
  Communism; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Troy (N.Y.); Communists; Ethnicity; Friendship; Jews, Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; General strikes |Z New York (State) |z Kings County; Welding; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Women welders; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; International Workers Order; Gimbel Brothers; New York Naval Shipyard
- Oral History Interview with Ida Pollack and Sylvia Everitt, April 24, 2008; 2010.003.019
  Ida Pollack (1922- ) grew up in the "Coops" or the United Workers Cooperative Colony, a predominantly Jewish and communist leaning housing cooperative built during the 1920s. She briefly attended Brooklyn College, but left to begin working, initially for a greeting card factory, then for Gimbels department store and eventually as a welder at the Brooklyn Navy Yard. Pollack was very active in political groups through her life, including the Young Communist League and the Local 22 of the Industrial Union of Marine and Shipbuilding Workers of America (IUMSWA). Sylvia Honigman Everitt (1921- ) was born on the Lower East Side but grew up in the Bronx in a Jewish family. Her father was a furrier. Everitt began working at the Navy Yard in 1942 after she graduated from Brooklyn College. She met her husband while working at the Navy Yard. Shortly after, he was drafted into the army and died in Germany just after the War ended.
  During their interview, Ida Pollack (1922- ) and Sylvia Honigman Everitt (1921- ) share stories about growing up in the Bronx and working together as welders at the Navy Yard. The two women discuss their long commute, socializing on Sands Street, union involvement and antagonism towards union organizers, uniforms, wages and working conditions. Pollack mentions getting a foot injury when a coated rod used for fusing metal accidentally dropped onto her shoe. She also discusses having to sign a loyalty oath, which was likely due to her involvement in radical political organizations. Both women discuss what it felt like to be a woman working at the Navy Yard and having to leave at the end of WWII. Also present at the time of the interview were Al Kolkin, Judy Kaplan (the daughter of Al Kolkin and Everitt and Honigman's good friend Lucy Kolkin) and Penny Lathars (Ida Pollack's daughter). Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan, Jennifer Egan and Daniella Romano.
  Communism; Communists; Sands Street (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Family life; Judaism; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Women welders; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; Everitt, Sylvia Honigman
- Oral History Interview with Leo Reitman, August 7, 1987; 1995.005.007
  Leo Reitman (ca. 1910s) grew up on the Lower East Side of Manhattan. He moved to Brooklyn after he began working at the Navy Yard. After leaving the Navy Yard, Reitman opened a grocery in Brooklyn.
  In his interview, Leo Reitman (ca. 1910s) discusses his work issuing stationary and hardware supplies to naval ships and shops at the Brooklyn Navy Yard. He also talks about his supervisors, wages, and gender relations and camaraderie within the Yard. Interview conducted by Benjamin Filene.
  Grocers; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Naval operations; World War, 1939-1945; Warships; Navy-yards and naval stations; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York Naval Shipyard; Reitman, Leo
- Oral History Interview with Charles Rocoff, July 24, 2006; 2010.003.038
  Charles Rocoff (1923- ) began working at the Brooklyn Navy Yard in 1942 shortly after finishing high school in Brooklyn. He worked for about one year as a pipefitter before going into the service in 1943.
  In his interview, Charles Rocoff (1923- ) explains his job as a pipefitter (plumber) for the ships at the Navy Yard, for which he primarily worked on repairs. He noticed that the British ships that he worked on were much dirtier than the American ships he repaired. Rocoff also talks about working with asbestos, training, security at the Yard and his coworkers. Interview conducted by Jennifer Egan.
  Warships; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Security systems; Plumbers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Asbestos; World War, 1939-1945; Draft; New York Naval Shipyard
- Oral History Interview with Rubena Ross, November 3, 2008; 2010.003.020
  Rubena Rhodes Ross (1918- ) was born in South Carolina where her mother was a teacher and her father was a farmer. Her family moved to Flushing, Queens when she was eleven and later settled in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, where she heard about work at the Navy Yard through her neighbors. Since Rhodes had learned to sew at an early age from her mother, she signed on to work as a seamstress in the flag loft at the Navy Yard.
  Rubena Rhodes Ross (1918- ) worked as a seamstress in a few factories before beginning work at the Navy Yard. During her interview, Ross describes the process of sewing the flags and her work environment. She remembers enjoying her work at the Navy Yard, relating that her supervisors did not just see her as a just worker, which was a different experience from her previous factory jobs. She also talks about her family, including her brother who was in the Airforce with the Tuskegee Airmen and her husband, who spent some time as a photographer for the Army. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan and Jennifer Egan.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); African Americans; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Friendship; Local transit; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Tailoring |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Wages |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Clothing and dress |z New York (State) |z New York; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; African American women; New York Naval Shipyard
- Oral History Interview with Catherine Sarnowski, November 4, 1987; 1995.005.006
  Catherine Sarnowski (ca. 1920- ) lived in the Bronx while working as a welder at the Brooklyn Navy Yard during World War II. She began as a tack welder and later was promoted to first class.
  In this brief interview, Catherine Sarnowski (ca. 1920- ) discusses her work as a welder, her long commute, working conditions at the Navy Yard, day trips and training for the job. She also talks about her experience working the night shift while going to school during the day. Interview conducted by Benjamin Filene.
  Ethnicity; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Friendship; Welding; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Accidents; World War, 1939-1945; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Armed Forces |x Civilian employees; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York Naval Shipyard; Sarnowski, Catherine Hennings
- Oral History Interview with Frank Siragusa, June 24, 2008; 2010.003.022
  Frank Siragusa (1928- ) grew up in uptown Manhattan in an Italian family. He quit school at 16 to work at the Brooklyn Navy Yard, since his father would not let him join the Navy. Siragusa worked at the Navy Yard for about six months. Before joining the Navy in 1945, Siragusa worked at a cheese factory and the Hotel New Yorker. He served four years in the Army, after which he went back to school on the GI Bill and became a musician and a music teacher. He later lived in Queens, Great Neck, NY and eventually retired and moved to Florida.
  During his interview, Frank Siragusa (1928- ) remembers his six months working as a painter at the Navy Yard. When he started, he painted pipes using lead paint, which injured his hands. After he recovered, he began working with a trompe l'oeil painter, who could make iron look like wood. He talks about his friendship with this painter, and the two of them discussing philosophy, spirituality and history. Siragusa worked a few other jobs before joining the Navy, including at the Hotel New Yorker, where he saw the plane crash into the Empire State Building in 1945, shortly before he enlisted. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Buddhism; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Great Neck (N.Y.); Queens (New York, N.Y.); Family; Immigrants; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Religion; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Transportation; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard
- Oral History Interview with Leo Skolnick, August 14, 1987; 1995.005.008
  Leo Skolnick (1909- ) worked at the Brooklyn Navy Yard from 1936 until 1948, when he left to study design and worked for several naval architects. He began working as an apprentice, and then as a sketcher in a sheet metal shop where shop drawings got fabricated. By the time Skolnick left the Yard, he was coordinating design drawings and supervising 200 to 300 workers.
  In his interview, Leo Skolnick (1909- ) details his job as a sketcher and supervisor of shop drawings at the Navy Yard. He also talks about several workplace accidents, working conditions, and feeling pride in his work at the Yard. Interview conducted by Benjamin Filene.
  Warships; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Friendship; Accidents; Supervisors; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; Missouri (Battleship: BB 63); Iowa (Battleship); Franklin (Aircraft carrier)
- Oral History Interview with James Smith, June 27, 2008; 2010.003.023
  James H. Smith (1927- ) grew up in Canarsie, New York, where his mother worked at a bakery and his father worked at a gas station. Smith was unable to serve in WWII because of his 4-F status, but instead began working at the Navy Yard at 16 or 17 as an outside machinist. He left when his family moved to Long Island, New York, where he worked at his father's gas station. Smith ended up working at Grumman Aerospace doing flight testing and remained for 39 years until he retired.
  During his interview, James H. Smith (1927- ) discusses his work at the Navy Yard as an outside machinist. He describes his job as a "gofer," running to get tools and coffee for others, and lending a hand where needed with mechanical work. Smith talks about security at the Navy Yard, seeing the progress the ships made when he left every day, and similarities between working at Grumman Aerospace and the Navy Yard. He also describes damaged ships returning from war, getting tools from the tool crib, social interactions during his lunch hour and being in awe of the size of the ships. Smith was upset with his 4-F status and explains how disappointed he was to leave the Navy Yard, where he felt he was contributing to the war effort. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Aircraft industry; Engineering; Family; Friendship; Machine shops; Security systems; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipfitting; Transportation; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard
- Oral History Interview with Henry Tatowicz, July 29, 1987; 1995.005.010
  Henry Tatowicz (ca. 1920- ) grew up in Brooklyn, NY. He worked as a third class machinist at the Brooklyn Navy Yard, working his way up to first class and eventually becoming a layout inspector, laying out castings for the machinists. His two brothers also worked at the Navy Yard. Tatowicz wanted to join the Army, but was asked to stay and work at the Navy Yard where his skills were needed.
  In this interview, Henry Tatowicz (ca. 1920- ) goes through the different positions he had at the Navy Yard, explaining the tools, supplies and work involved in each position. He also talks about workplace safety, working the night shift, women at the Yard, his feelings about the reductions in the workforce after the war, and changes in Brooklyn his lifetime. Tatowicz remembers working at the Yard and hearing about the events at Pearl Harbor. He was able to use his skills from working on the machines at the Navy Yard in future positions after he left. Interview conducted by Benjamin Filene.
  Warships; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Pearl Harbor (Hawaii), Attack on, 1941; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; Tatowicz, Henry
- Oral History Interview with Ernest Thompson, May 18, 2009; 2010.003.047
  Ernest Thompson (1917- ) was born in Byronville, Georgia and grew up as the oldest of six children in Americus, Georgia. For the first five years of Thompson's life his father worked as a farmer. When the family moved to Americus Thompson's father worked for a lumber company. Upon graduation from high school in 1936, Thompson enlisted in the Navy and went to boot camp in Norfolk, Virginia. Before World War II, Thompson was assigned to the Tennessee battleship. In 1940, Thompson left the service and got married. He took a job as a laborer in Los Angeles for the Sub-Pacific Railroad and was promoted to boilermaker apprentice where he learned about steelwork and ironwork. He then went to work for the city of Los Angeles and got called back into service as a second class petty officer and was quickly promoted to first class based on his work experience. He was given orders to go to Philadelphia to take classes on engineering spaces in Navy ships. Upon completion of school, he chose to work on the Missouri and moved to the Flushing Avenue Barracks in the Brooklyn Navy Yard in March 1944. Thompson worked on the engineering spaces of the Missouri throughout World War II in No. 4 Boiler Room and was onboard Missouri during the surrender of Japan.
  During the interview, Ernest Thompson (1917- ) talks about growing up in Georgia and why he decided to enlist in the Navy. Thompson describes the jobs his brothers did during World War II. He discusses how his work as a boiler apprentice helped his career working in engineering spaces in the Navy. He describes life at the Brooklyn Navy Yard and living and working in the engineering spaces of the Missouri. He recounts, in great detail, eating breakfast onboard the Missouri the morning of the surrender of Japan. He also recounts his experience trying to get home to southern California at the end of World War II. Interview conducted at the U.S.S. Missouri Reunion in Virginia on May 18, 2009. Interview conducted by Daniella Romano.
  Engineering; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); California; Georgia; Virginia; Engineers; Warships; Navy-yards and naval stations; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York Naval Shipyard; Missouri (Battleship: BB 63)
- Oral History Interview with Frank Trezza, October 9, 2009; 2010.003.025
  Frank J. Trezza (1952- ) was hired by Seatrain Shipbuilding as a Mechanic Helper at the Brooklyn Navy Yard in 1973 and eventually worked his way up to the position of First Class Marine Electrician. He worked at the Navy Yard until 1978 when he was injured on the job and told by doctors that he would never work in the shipbuilding profession again. Following rehabilitation from his injuries, Mr. Trezza relocated to Maine where he resumed working as a First Class Marine Electrician at Bath Iron Works, the Portsmouth Naval Shipyard in New Hampshire, and in South America for a European defense contractor. In 1999, Mr. Trezza earned a Bachelor of Arts degree in economics from the University of Southern Maine, and in 2007, he published the book, Brooklyn: Steel-Blood Tenacity, a memoir of the years he spent working at the Brooklyn Navy Yard.
  In this interview, Frank J. Trezza discuss his experiences as a marine electrician for Seatrain Shipbuilding in the Navy Yard in the 1970s, the injury that lost him the job, and his subsequent career at other shipyards. Through this discussion, he also touches on national and international politics of shipbuilding, his photography of the Yards, and the writing of his book. He also talks about his training at the Food and Maritime Trades Vocational High School. He tells about his family's four-generation history in Brooklyn, including several family members who worked at the Navy Yard. His wife, Millie, was also present for the interview, and she told the story of their courtship and marriage. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Dating (Social customs); Sheepshead Bay (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Accidents; Family; Labor leaders; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Shipfitting; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ships; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Welding; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; International Workers Order; Trezza, Frank J.; Seatrain Shipbuilding Corp; New York Naval Shipyard
- Oral History Interview with Abraham Weintraub, July 8, 2008; 2010.003.024
  Abraham Weintraub (1910-2010) lived in Brooklyn for his whole life. In addition to working at the Navy Yard, Weintraub worked for his brother-in-law who manufactured education toys and handler for the US Post Office. He also participated in several marathons and races after retiring from the Post Office.
  During his interview, Abraham Weintraub (1910-2010), explains his work as a chipper and caulker at the Navy Yard, where he made sure rivets were watertight. Along with his daughter and son (Florence and Irwin Weintraub), Weintraub talks about working on the USS Missouri, the other workers at the Navy Yard and competing in marathons and other races in New York and Massachusetts. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Family; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipfitting; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sex role; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; Missouri (Battleship: BB 63)
- Oral History Interview with Milton Wurtzel, February 12, 2009; 2010.003.002
  Milton Wurtzel (1919- ) was born in Manhattan and grew up in the Bronx and in Stuyvesant Heights, Brooklyn on Kosciusko Street. Wurtzel worked at Lieberman Shoe Factory as a foreman and at a slipper factory before he started working at the Brooklyn Navy Yard as a welder. Wurtzel left the Brooklyn Navy Yard when he was inducted into the Navy, in which he worked on the USS Humboldt. At the time of the interview, Wurtzel was living in Long Island.
  In his interview, Milton Wurtzel (1919- ) gives many details and stories about his experience at the Brooklyn Navy Yard and in the US Navy. He describes the process of welding, the tools he used, his training and supervisors, the sickbay, the cafeteria and lunchtime, driving to work and theft at the yard. In one story, he explains how he made jewelry using the Hammerhead Crane. In another, he discusses the unhygienic conditions on French ships. He also discusses his Jewish background, growing up in Brooklyn and the Bronx, meeting his wife and Navy life aboard the USS Humboldt. Wurtzel's grandson Jason Wurtzel was also present at the time of the interview. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Cranes, derricks, etc; Stuyvesant Heights (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Dating (Social customs); Ethnicity; Fishing; Friendship; Judaism; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Local transit; Sailors; Security systems; Sex role; Shipfitting; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Transportation; Wages |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; Missouri (Battleship: BB 63)
- Oral History Interview with Howard Zinn, December 8, 2008; 2010.003.041
  Howard Zinn (1922-2010) grew up in Brooklyn, New York. He began working at the Brooklyn Navy Yard as an apprentice after taking a civil service test in 1940. Because he worked at the Navy Yard, his family was able to move into a housing project in Fort Greene, Brooklyn. Zinn left the Navy Yard to join the Air Force in 1943. He later went on to become an historian, author and activist.
  During his interview, Howard Zinn (1922-2010) explains how he ended up working at the Brooklyn Navy Yard and details his work there as an apprentice shipfitter. He says the best part of his time at the Navy Yard was organization the Apprentice Association, which was an organization of apprentices who were not allowed to be a part of the American Federation of Labor unions at the Yard. He also talks about his salary, organizing a basketball team, commuting to work from Fort Greene, uniforms, witnessing a workplace accident, and race and ethnicity. Interview conducted by Daniella Romano.
  Warships; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Labor |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Ethnicity; Apprentices; Accidents; Public housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Wages |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipfitting; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard
- Oral History Interview with Carmela Zuza, July 3, 2008; 2010.003.001